Within this task, we shall give a marking
that has no successor marking and in each
case, we shall also say which transitions
must be fired in sequence to reach that marking.
And we have been given these three nets here
and we start with the first one.
In order to find such marking where no further
marking can be reached, we can actually try
a sequence.
And when we start with this Petri Net here,
there's only one option or one transition
we can fire and this is T2.
So, anyways, it has to start with T2.
So, we can start with T2 and when we process
this transition, when we fire it then there
will be markings in S2 and S3 because of these
arrows here going out from T2.
And when we have reached this marking here,
then we can either execute T3 or T1 so we
can fire T1 or we can fire T2.
And let's say we fire T1.
So, when we do that, we remove one token from
S2 and add a token in S1.
And now, there is still another reachable marking
as we can still fire T3.
And when we do this, so let me properly remove
those tokens here.
So, when we process T3 then we can remove
this token here as well.
And then we are in this marking here now,
we can fire no more transition.
So, we reached a final marking.
And now we can name actually this marking
as we know which marking it is.
In S1 there are two tokens and in
S2, there are zero tokens.
And this goes also for S3 and also for S4.
So, this is the first option that we have
found the first net but of course, we could
have also chosen to go another way.
So if I undo these steps here and go back
to the beginning, then I said when we fire
T2, then we were in this state here, and then
we chose a transition, so we chose T1 to fire
but we could have chosen T3 as well.
So if we choose T3 first, then also in this
marking we can also choose only one transition,
but it's T1 in this case, so we get the same
result, it's still this marking but another
sequence.
So, either one of those sequences is fine.
So either this one or that one is fine for
the first Petri Net.
Now, let's see for the second Petri Net what
we can do here.
So, again, as I said we can execute the Petri
Net until we reach a point where nothing is
possible anymore.
And for this Petri Net, we can choose T1 or
T2 at the beginning.
And when we look at this one here this looks
quite promising so we could choose T2 to fire
and in this case we would get to this point
here where... So, well this was the sequence.
I'll write it down here below.
So, when we just execute T2 then we are already
in the final marking because there is no transition
that we can fire now because T2 requires a
token in S1 and so does T1, and T3 requires
a token in S2.
So, now we have reached a final marking and
we can name it by saying S1 has zero tokens,
S2 has zero tokens, S3 has one token, and
S4 has zero tokens.
So, in this case, we just execute T two and
we are done.
But as I said we could have chosen a different
way here because we had the option of firing
T1 and T2 at the beginning.
So, if we fire T1, then we get into this state
here.
And now, in this state, we can only fire T3.
So, we can't fire T2 because it requires a
token in S1, and also T1 requires one.
So it can only fire T3.
But if we do so, then we get a token in S4
and as well in S1.
And when we are in this state, we can fire
again either T1 or T2.
So, if we fire T2 at this time, then we get
one token in S3.
And now we’ve reached a different marking.
So, in this case, this one should be the
same, but S4 would be one in this case.
Let me write this arrow again.
So, S4 would be one and in order to reach
this sequence, we executed first of all
T1 then T3, and then T2.
And in this case, we could have chosen to
go further on, so we could have chosen T1.
T3 this was the state that we executed before.
So now in this state, we could once more fire
T1.
So, by firing T1 at this stage we get the token
into S2 and remove it from S1.
And now we can fire only one transition again
and this is T3 in this case.
So now if you fire T3 we get another token
in S4 and again a token in S1 and the token
in S2 is removed.
So we can fire T3 here once more
and then again we can either fire T2 which
will get the token here and we have reached a
final marking as we can fire no more transition
now.
And I think you’ve got the point so in this
case, we have another marking, this S4 having
two tokens.
And we could continue this game more often.
So we could after processing T1, T3, T1, T3,
we could go further on with that until we
finally fire T2 but there are no further options
but cycling in this case.
Now let's consider the last Petri Net N3.
And in this case, there is only T3 active,
so we can only fire T3.
We cannot fire T2 because it requires a token
in S4 and we cannot fire T1 because it also
requires a token in S4.
But we can fire T3 as it requires a token
in S3 which there is and a token in S2 which
there is as well.
And as we can fire this transition we have
not reached a final marking but when we fire
this transition we’ll remove one token from
S3 and we remove one token from S2, but we
place a token again back into S2.
So I can put this token back in here and we
add a token in S4.
And this, I'll call it T3, and we could now either
fire T1 or T2 because both just require a
token in S4 but we cannot fire T3 as it requires
a token S3.
If we fire T1, so let's fire T1.
We remove a token from S4 and get a token
into S1.
So now this is a marking without successor because
now we can't fire any transition anymore.
T1, and T2, both require a token in S4, and
T3 requires a token in S3.
And so, this would be the marking that we
have.
So, S1 would be one, S2 would be one and S3
would be zero and S4 would also be zero.
But as I said in the previous step before
executing T1, so, after executing T3 in this
state here we could have also fired T2.
So, this would be another option, if we have
T3 and then fire T2, then we would remove
one token here and add it right up here into
S3.
So, if you do this, we have again/ so this
was T2, we have again the initial state and
now we could again execute either sequence.
So we could execute T3/T1 which will lead
us to a final marking which will of course
be the same as before.
Or we could again fire T3 and then T2, so
either of these sequences would be okay.
So, for instance, T3/T2/T3/T1 would be another
option of a sequence that will lead to the
same marking without successor.
So, if you have any sequence that starts with
T3/T2 and then followed by T3/T1 then you
have the sequence correct for this Petri Net
as well.